Guide to the University Hospital records, 1898-2004 RG0061
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
University Hospital records
1898-2004
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
George Washington University. Hospital
RG0061
20.25 Linear Feet
Collection includes the School of Nursing Alumnae Association meetings journal and the Medical Staff Executive Committee and Department minutes.
Restrictions on Access
Series 1 is closed to research for 25 years from date of record creation.
Some series are not completely processed. Please see staff for assistance.
Acquisition Information
Materials acquired through transfers from the University Hospital.
Historical Note
In 1847 the medical department of Columbian College became the National Medical College. In the early 1850s, it was in the forefront of medical education in the nation.
The GW infirmary was enlarged in 1853, in response to growing need. The improved facility allowed the faculty to include clinical studies formally in the curriculum. Since few schools taught clinical medicine before the early twentieth century, this addition was remarkable in its foresight.
The following years were prosperous ones for the GW Infirmary, but with the beginning to the American Civil War in 1861, the school entered a difficult era. Both medical students and faculty joined forces in the North and the South, though their numbers were significantly higher among the Confederate ranks. Beginning a long tradition of GW service to presidents, Dr. A.Y.P. Garnett left Washington to become Jefferson Davis's personal physician, while Dr. Robert King Stone remained to serve Abraham Lincoln.
After the war began, the government reclaimed the Infirmary for use as a military hospital, and less than seven months later the building was destroyed by fire. The Washington Star of November 4, 1861, headlined the disaster with "The Burning of the E Street Infirmary Terrible and Thrilling Incidents--Removal of More than One Hundred Patients." This ended GW's first established teaching hospital.
Despite the chaos of the war, the medical college regrouped and in 1863 reopened in the Constitution Office on E Street between 12th and 13th Streets, NW. From 1865 to 1867 it shared space in the Columbia College Law Building on 5th Street between D and E Streets, NW. The building also served as a church on Sundays.
The GW hospital and medical school moved to 1335 H Street in 1868. The new building previously housed the Army Medical Museum's specimens and was donated by W.W. Corcoran. This was GW's main hospital until 1948.
The GW University Hospital (on 23rd Street, GW campus) was completed and opened in 1948. The Meyer Pavilion was added in 1968, Duncan Pavilion in 1978 and the Southeast addition in 1978. A new GW Hospital was completed in 2002 and located on 23rd Street north of the Foggy Bottom Metro stop.
This note was written in 2005
Scope and Contents
Materials in this collection include the School of Nursing Alumnae Association meetings journal and the Medical Staff Executive Committee and Department minutes. The materials range in date from 1898 to 2004.
Collection Organization
Organized into three series: Committee and department minutes; Nursing alumnae association; and Office files
Washington (D.C.); Biography; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; By-laws; Nurses; George Washington University
- Committee and department minutes, 1974-1989; RG0061 Series 1; 19.5 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series consists of medical staff executive committee and department meeting minutes. Other committee files include Credentials, By-Laws, and Patient Advocacy. The materials range in date from 1974-89.
  - Hospital Space Committee, 01/1981-02/1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Executive Committee, 12/1969-08/1975 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Executive Committee, 01/1975-12/1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Executive Committee, 01/1976-06/1976 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Executive Committee, 07/1977-12/1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Executive Committee, 01/1977-05/1977 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Executive Committee, 01/1978-05/1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Executive Committee, 05/1978-12/1978 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Executive Committee, 01/1979-05/1979 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Executive Committee, 06/1979-10/1979 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Executive Committee, 11/1979-03/1980 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Executive Committee, 04/1980-08/1980 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Executive Committee, 09/1980-12/1980 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Executive Committee, 01/1981-03/1981 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Executive Committee, 06/1981-12/1981 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Executive Committee, 07/1982-12/1982 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Executive Committee, 01/1982-06/1982 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Executive Committee, 06/1983-09/1983 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Executive Committee, 10/1983-12/1983 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Executive Committee, 01/1983-03/1983 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Executive Committee, 04/1983-05/1983 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Executive Committee, 01/1984-03/1984 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Executive Committee, 04/1984-05/1984 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Executive Committee, 06/1984-08/1984 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Executive Committee, 09/1984-10/1984 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Executive Committee, 11/1984-12/1984 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Executive Committee, 07/1976-12/1976 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Executive Committee, 01/1985-02/1985 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Executive Committee, 06/1985-08/1985 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Executive Committee, 09/1985-11/1985 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Executive Committee, 12/1985-02/1986 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Executive Committee, 06/1986-08/1986 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Executive Committee, 03/1986-05/1986 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Urology, 12/1986-12/1982 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Radiology, 12/1986-01/1977 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Pathology, 12/1986-02/1976 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Pathology, 10/1986-03/1979 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Department of Nursing, 06/1986-12/1982 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Department of Nursing, 09/1982-05/1979 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Clinical Engineering, 04/1980-07/1976 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Child Health and Development, 12/1986-10/1980 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Anesthesiology, 03/1987-12/1975 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Therapeutics Committee, 04/1974-12/1986 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Utilization Reviewand Medical Audit Committee, 12/1978-03/1974 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Utilization Review and Quality Assessment Committee, 12/1986-01/1979 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Resuscitation Team Committee, 10/1986-01/1974 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Surgical Case Review Committee, 10/1986-09/1975 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Dermatology, 10/1986-08/1976 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Emergency Medicine, 12/1986-06/1984 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Health Care Sciences, 02/1983-07/1979 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Medicine Departmental Meetings, 12/1986-03/1980 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Medicine: Division of Rehabilitation Medicine, 12/1986-01/1980 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Obstetrics/Gynecology, 05/1986-10/1975 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Ophthalmology, 12/1986-06/1982 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Neurological Surgery, 12/1985-10/1975 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Neurology, 12/1986-10/1984 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Bylaws Committee, 11/1986-09/1974 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Bylaws Committee: Non-Physician Professional Material, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Blood Bank Advisory Committee, 10/1986-01/1981 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Cancer Committee, 11/1986-12/1980 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Credentials Committee, 1978-1980 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Credentials Committee, 01/1981-12/1982 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Credentials Committee, 01/1983-12/1983 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Credentials Committee, 01/1984-12/1984 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Patient Care Committee, 11/1986-06/1982 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Patient Education Committee, 11/1986-11/1981 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Infection Control Committee, 11/1986-06/1979 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Medical Records Committee, 12/1986-12/1979 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Operating Room Committee, 11/1986-06/1979 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Patient Advocacy Committee, 12/1976-12/1979 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Patient Advocacy Committee, 10/1982-07/1974 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Patient Advocacy Committee, 12/1976-06/1985 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Patient Safety Committee, 12/1977-06/1976 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Patient Safety Committee, 12/1978-06/1978 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Patient Safety Committee, 09/1981-01/1979 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Patient Safety Committee, 11/1984-01/1982 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Patient Safety Committee, 12/1986-02/1985 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Radiation Safety Committee, 11/1986-02/1974 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Safety, Fire, and Accident Prevention, 05/1980-08/1977 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Quality Assurance, 08/1986-05/1981 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Executive Committee, 09/1986-12/1986 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Quarterly Staff, 09/1976-12/1978 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Chief Residents Meeting, 03/1974-12/1989 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Quarterly Staff Conference, 09/1970-06/1976 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Annual and Quarterly Staff, 12/1978-03/1980 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Quarterly Staff Conference, 09/1980-06/1981 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Quarterly Staff Conference, 09/1981-12/1983 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Quarterly Staff Conference, 1984-1986 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Quarterly Reports, 09/1977-09/1985 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Credentials Committee, 01/1985-12/1985 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Credentials Committee, 01/1986-12/1986 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Critical Care Advisory Committee, 11/1986-12/1980 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Dialysis and Transplantation Committee, 10/1986-12/1977 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Disaster Committee, 12/1986-02/1981 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Dietetics Committee, 09/1986-05/1974 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Human Research Committee, 12/1986-11/1979 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Medical Staff Ethics Committee, 12/1986-07/1985 (Box 13, Folder 8)
- Nursing alumnae association, 1914-1932; RG0061 Series 2; 0.25 Linear feet (Box 1)
  This series consists of a School of Nursing alumnae association meetings journal, and dates from 1914-32.
  - Meeting Minutes for the Nursing School Alumnae Association, 1914-1932 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Office files, 1898-2004; RG0061 Series 3; 0.5 Linear feet (Box 1, Box 2)
  This series contains brochures, reports, newsletters, comment cards, forms, memorandum, floor plans, handbooks, a key chain, a bookmark, press releases, by-laws, rules, regulations, correspondence, questionnaires, manuals, guides, speech, biographical information, invitations, interview transcript, and programs. They range in date from 1898 to 2004. The materials concern the University Hospital; buildings; internships; residency; fellowships; the Pain Management Center; donations; the Board of Governors; annual reports; "Progress Report: The George Washington University Hospital Equipment Fund"; fundraising; information for patients; the Respiratory and Rehabilitation Center; research; School of Nursing; staff; Houseofficers' manuals; the Woman's Board; history; alumni information; Nurse Pomroy during the civil war, Columbian Hospital, and events.
  - History of GW Civil War Columbian Hospital, 02/04/2004 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Hospital, 09/23/1946-08/2002 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Hospital - Agreement for Merger Between The GWU and The Garfield Memorial Hospital and the Washington Home For Foundlings, January 21, 1927, 01/21/1927 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Hospital--Annual Report Of The University Hospital, 1898-1901, 11/01/1898-10/31/1901 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Hospital--Annual Report Of The University Hospital, 1903-1916, 04/1903-1916 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Hospital History Floor plans Washington Circle, 1948-2002, 09/23/1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Hospital History Program of Development Report, 1972, 05/1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Hospital History - Washington Circle, 1948-1997, 1946-01/10/1966 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Hospital History - Washington Circle, 1998-2002, 02/26/1998-08/2002 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Hospitals - Officers & Medical Board - By-Laws, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Hospital--Patient Information Publications, 1969-10/1978 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Hospital Respiratory and Rehabilitation Center Annual Report, 1958, 07/01/1958-06/30/1959 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Hospital - School of Nursing, 05/23/1906-1931 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Hospital--Staff, Medical--By-Laws, Rules, Regulations, 1909-1959 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Hospital--Staff, Medical--Nurses, 12/28/1898-06/08/1959 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Hospital--Staff, Medical--Physicians, 1945-1960 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Hospital--Staff, Medical--Procedures Manuals, 1969-07/1977 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Hospital--Staff, Non- Medical--Grievances, 02/15/1974-1974 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Hospital--Staff, Non-Medical-- Individuals, 1948-1968 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Hospital--Women's Board, 1928-08/25/2000 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Hospital--Women's Board--Events, 1927-05/03/1949 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Hospital--Women's Board History, 12/07/1907-04/23/1956 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Hospital--Women's Board History 100th Anniversary, 03/1998-04/07/1998 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Hospital--Women's Board History Oral History, 1981, 02/11/1981 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Hospital--Women's Board--Lists of Members, 1935-35, 1946, 1975, 1996, 1935-1997 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - George Washington University Hospital Proposal, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Scope and Contents
    Printed by AMI: The International Health Care Services Company.
  - Group photograph portrait of the American Laryngological Association, 1929 (Oversize data_value_missing_3bb1af9218bde7be1dcd5fd411edc6fa)
    This is a group photograph portrait of the American Laryngological Association, including Charles W. Richardson.Group photograph portrait of the American Laryngological Association, including Charles W. Richardson.